<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://aleshe04.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://aleshe04.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-28T16:58:43+00:00</updated><id>https://aleshe04.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on Decolonization: Why the Hell This Is Still a Conversation</title><link href="https://aleshe04.github.io/blog/2024/thoughts-on-decolonization-why-the-hell-this-is-still-a-conversation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Decolonization: Why the Hell This Is Still a Conversation"/><published>2024-04-15T18:52:45+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T18:52:45+00:00</updated><id>https://aleshe04.github.io/blog/2024/thoughts-on-decolonization-why-the-hell-this-is-still-a-conversation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aleshe04.github.io/blog/2024/thoughts-on-decolonization-why-the-hell-this-is-still-a-conversation/"><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="Young men surrounded by a cheering crowd tearing down the statue of Cecil John Rhodes at the University of Cape Town." src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/780/1*o8vlt5VKMdGR7hT8aEwa6g.jpeg"/><figcaption>Students at the University of Cape Town in South Africa during the 2015 “<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/2015/nov/18/why-south-african-students-have-turned-on-their-parents-generation">Rhodes Must Fall</a>” protests (The Guardian)</figcaption></figure> <p>Yesterday, just before I fell asleep, rage — in all its pulsating, blood stirring heat, came and settled violently at the bottom of my stomach. Unsurprisingly, I had been reading the news. Particularly, news pertaining to life and individual identity across the African continent. This rage was followed quite quickly by a biting chill I can only attribute to sadness, before rapidly transforming into a fiery optimism — an optimism steeped deeply in hope, ambition, and a fervent love for this planet we currently call our home. In this whirlwind of emotion, this whirlwind of continuous reflection about African development, I began thinking acutely about the phenomenon of decolonization. In specific, how we are not as free as we purport to be.</p> <p>The art of decolonization is a rather delicate one, in that it often requires a gruesome, distressing and riotous process — a process which revolves around the deconstruction of one’s warped worldview, specifically regarding their own indigenous identity. To decolonize, boiled down to its intrinsic essence, is to reevaluate. To interrogate the very nature of the violent, oppressive structures that ensure the continuous marginalization of African identity — of African languages, of African cultures, and of African personhood. It is to rethink the world we have been given in all its bloodiness and its brutality, and it is to radically question this seemingly innate desire to decimate peoples deemed as “different” or “other,” by the powers that be. To decolonize is to theorize. To construct a society of kindness, equity, and collectivist culture through constant and consistent reflection.</p> <p>Many believe that decolonization is simply the mass exodus of Europeans from the African continent in the mid-to-late 1900s. By that metric, decolonization was achieved decades ago, by impassioned revolutionaries at the forefront of the war against colonial subjugation. In truth, decolonization is a concept much more layered than that — it is complex, multidimensional.</p> <p>Conversations regarding colonization and imperialism more often than not, engage with the phenomenon through a lens rooted solely in the physical. It is, in many instances, a discussion concerning the tangible impacts of occupation, and not the harmful mental and psychological effects induced by centuries of white supremacist degradation. Europeans did not solely come to Africa to seize land for their own selfish economic gains. To view colonization entirely through that perspective, is to dishonor the histories of millions of indigenous African peoples. While colonial institutions were indeed driven by an insatiable hunger for land and domination, they also sought to obliterate any semblance of African identity present within the Continent. It was through their destruction of the very fabric of African cultural tradition, that they were then able to achieve their diabolic aim of European dominion.</p> <p>This destruction was, predictably, realized through a variety of exceedingly cruel manners. The French policy of assimilation — a policy which intended to forcibly remodel African peoples into caricatures of French citizens (with the aim of erasing the customs present within these societies), is a rather prominent example. The violent razing of shrines and places of worship is another, and the portrayal of poetic African languages as a series of grunts and groans, in a bid to aggrandize English, French, Portuguese and other European languages, is yet another instance. The European refusal to engage with the political and judicial systems of African peoples (particularly those systems held at the helm by women), their characterisation of African dress as “barbaric” and “uncouth,” and their confinement of gender into two rigid Western binaries, ensured that Africans would forever remain attached to a Euro-American understanding of the world they inhabited. An understanding which would persist long after their colonizers had gathered their belongings and gone.</p> <p>European colonization found much of its success in its destruction of African cultural elements and practices. They not only dominated Africans physically (as is often taught), but commandeered Africans culturally and intellectually. Most effective of all, was their inculcation of the deformed idea that Africans and blackness at its crux, were innately inferior to European identity — an idea which has unfortunately found a foothold in the psyche of millions of Africans today.</p> <p>I used to hate how my dark, kinky hair twisted tightly, and often painfully, around the tooth of a comb. It was a marker of blackness — a constant reminder of my <em>own</em> internalized inferiority. This feeling was exacerbated at school, where we idolized whiteness and the West; where we debated whether or not we deserved emancipation from colonial occupation, and where we learned that in order to solve our current social, political and economic situation, we needed to worship conformity and Western dominion over our nations and identities. At the time, Nigeria, my nation of origin, had been “independent” — set free from the throes of colonial rule for almost sixty years. Yet, my educators seemed to salivate at the prospect of a return to such a world order.</p> <p>They resolutely informed us of the “good” that colonialism brought about, reeling off hollow diction and ignorant reasoning; “They gave us phones and clothes and democracy” they said, conveniently forgetting the violence and destruction imperialist subjugation wreaked upon our parents and grandparents. We were told that the white man should never have left, and the impressionable minds of my peers and I drank in this information, like a thirsty animal stumbling upon a watering hole. This dislike for my hair quickly graduated into dislike for my skin. My home. My Continent. I would long for the white man to come and liberate me. To free me from the shackles of my dark and decrepit Africa.</p> <p>At this same institution, we were warned against speaking “vernacular,” the school’s code for indigenous African languages. Each whisper of Yoruba or Igbo was met with austere punishment — a swift rap on the knuckles with a wooden ruler, or an unreasonable physical demand chosen in particular for its ability to humiliate. To tame our accents (lest we sounded poor — or worse, African), we were required to participate in “Diction-in-English” classes, where we were taught to enunciate certain words in the manner the British do. Where we were taught the subtle art of imitation, and where we were made to realize that if we did not sound or act a certain way, we would be relegated to the role of stupid, poor, inarticulate African, forever bound by our inability to assimilate to whiteness.</p> <p>It is of course unsurprising why many Africans are enormously ashamed. Ashamed of their names, ashamed of their origins, ashamed of their identities. A few months ago, the speaker of the Kenyan parliament banned traditional African attire in the parliament’s debate chambers, citing its “inappropriateness” as the driving factor behind his decision. He deemed coats, collars, and ties the proper mode of dressing, arguing that any other forms of clothing were “negating a set standard.” The same standards established by Kenya’s power-drunk colonizers who, in their quest to dominate and destroy, massacred thousands of peoples and imprisoned over a million others during their repressive regime. To discard and to demonize tangible aspects of one’s culture in a misguided attempt to pander to the West — the West, who have already made it rather clear what they think of Africa, is not only an affront to African identity, but an attack on “African-ness” in its entirety.</p> <p>Across the border in Uganda, anti-LGBTQ+ discrimination runs rampant, cemented in legislation aiming to further marginalize and oppress a people of an already precarious status. Yoweri Museveni — the dictator of the East African nation, claims that this decision is as a result of his desire to protect the sanctity of African traditional values, from the corrupt and immoral behaviors of the West. Yet, queerness is not a Western import as alleged by him and many other Africans. Historically, Africa has always been queer. In Uganda specifically, many ethnic groups were indifferent to same-sex relationships and gender-non-conforming identities, some even placing these identities at the forefront of certain cultural practices. In Angola, the Chibados — people of a third gender, often held places in court and performed crucial rituals, possessing positions of utmost importance within their communities.</p> <p>In several other African ethnic groups, ideas regarding gender were vast and varied, unable to be confined to a binary. Much of this changed rather rapidly with the imposition of anti-sodomy laws by Europeans. Spurred by their Victorian understandings of sex and gender, colonial officials deemed these behaviors deviant and obscene, leading to the birth of unbridled homophobia and the retention of these anti-sodomy laws by African nations — laws which now claim the lives of many across the Continent today.</p> <p>When we direct the conversation to feminism and feminist thought, we realize that much of the current treatment of women across Africa is also as a result of colonial oppression. Africans are not intrinsically anti-feminist, although many in the Global North would vehemently disagree with such an assertion. In order to understand the continuous marginalization of women in modern African society, one must understand and acknowledge the historical processes that have led to this point. Women in pre-colonial Africa were in many cases, revered and respected. They held important political roles, ran markets, performed crucial duties in religious practice, and led (and populated) armies. The Agojie of Dahomey, Queen Nzinga of the Mbandu people, and Yaa Asentewa of the Ashanti Empire are prime examples of this phenomenon. This, like much of African society, changed incredibly quickly after the advent of colonization. Colonial officials, unable to grasp a world so distinctly different from their own comprehensions of gender, refused to engage with women who held political power.</p> <p>They focused instead on the systematic erasure of these identities from the political sphere, restricting their access to land, wealth, autonomy and authority. It is therefore not unpredictable that, eventually, women across the Continent would begin to be treated in the repressive manners in which they are at present.</p> <p>I am not arguing that pre-colonial Africa was a utopia, nor am I arguing that patriarchal societies and thought did not exist within the African continent. In all honesty, pre-colonial Africa was frightening in its own right. I am simply stating that the understanding of, and the scholarship revolving around the histories of not only African women, but African identity holistically, has lacked a nuanced and multidimensional outlook. An illustration could be Africa’s reduction to “femicide capital of the world,” without regard for the history of imported violence that has shaped such a frightening statistic.</p> <p>It is not astonishing that our hatred for others keeps us hostage, its sharp knife pressed against the skin of our throats. It is not astonishing that we as a people are xenophobic, sexist, homophobic, self-loathing, anti-intellectual, so attached to radically conservative understandings of religion, so intolerant of identities which do not conform to Western notions of personhood. We have been stolen from. We have been told that we are not enough. What else are we to do? What else are we to think?</p> <p>When people ask, often dismissively, why discourse about decolonization is still ongoing, they refuse to acknowledge the fact that we are currently colonized within the margins of our own homeland. The difference now, is that it is our once radical and liberatory thought — our understanding of ourselves, our histories, and our identities, that have been chained and left to decay in a prison of colonial construction. We cannot purport to be decolonized if people are continuously marginalized within our societies. We cannot purport to be decolonized if we eschew collective action, collective culture, and collective politics, for money and capital. We cannot purport to be decolonized if we worship the West, at the expense of the development of our Continent and its peoples.</p> <p>If Africa is to stand a chance, we must free ourselves from the cold, brutal shackles of this veneration of white mediocrity. We must set this thinking — this thinking that we are inherently subordinate, suboptimal, <em>subaltern — </em>we must set it ablaze. And we must watch intensely as it burns to the ground, bringing along with it systems which do not serve our interests, systems which seek to further denigrate our communities: the IMF and the Global North monopoly on African finances. Passport privilege. Neocolonialism, and the violent, capitalist exploitation of African peoples by Western corporations. We must bury those ashes, planting instead seeds of progressive thought, watering them, and ensuring their germination into large, leafy trees of liberation. Trees underneath which we may speak, and think, and love.</p> <p>We must decolonize. And we must begin doing so now.</p> <p>Decolonization is not simply a “return” to the way in which things were done in Africa before the beginnings of its exploitation. As I mentioned earlier, pre-colonial Africa was not utopic. To decolonize, is to question everything we have been fed about the world we inhabit. It is to ask why Africans in government are ashamed to don traditional attire, and it is to interrogate why there is a refusal to engage with indigenous dialects, while English and French are celebrated and esteemed. It is to take our answers to these questions, to analyze them rigorously, and to formulate new manners of worldbuilding. It is to dissect religion, its effects on politics, and the role it plays not only in our lives, but on a larger societal scale. It is to continue asking, and it is to continue thinking, and it is to love ourselves fiercely and beautifully, in a world where we have been told that we do not deserve such love.</p> <p>Decolonization does not mean to send white people packing, or to throw away English, nor does it mean that we must discard our jeans in lieu of flowy <em>agbadas </em>and <em>dashikis</em>. It is to examine why we wear jeans and we speak English in the first place, and it is to remember that inasmuch as we do these things, we are African, first and foremost. It is to imagine the Africa of our dreams, and it is to fight tooth and nail towards achieving such an ideal. Decolonization is many things, but in summary, it is to care for ourselves. It is to care for our people as thoughtfully and as deeply as we can.</p> <p>We have a long journey ahead of us. Let us begin by asking questions.</p> <p>— Lekan :)</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=604f09872c32" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>